Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是斯科特-曼利
Every time I show this film of the launch of Explorer 1,
每次我播放这段探索者1号的发射影片时 人们都会问我 为什么火箭的机头会旋转？
people ask me why is the nose of that rocket spinning.
人们都会问我 为什么那枚火箭的机头在旋转
And this spin is an example of a common technique in rocket launches used to help with stability.
而这个旋转是火箭发射中常用的技术的一个例子 用来帮助稳定
At the time it was really a quick hack by the army's ballistic missiles team headed by Wernher von Braun
在当时 这确实是由沃纳-冯-布劳恩领导的军队弹道导弹小组的一个快速黑客技术
so that they would be in a position to be able to launch a satellite into orbit before anybody else.
的弹道导弹小组 以便他们能够在其他人之前将卫星发射到轨道上
They had the Jupiter C rocket and they developed it
他们有木星C火箭 他们开发了它
and demonstrated everything they needed to put a satellite into orbit
并展示了他们将卫星送入轨道所需的一切
but the politics at the time was a little sensitive
但当时的政治有点敏感
and they didn't get to go until after the navy's Vanguard had failed
他们直到海军的先锋号失败后才开始行动
but then they would prove the design in January of 1958.
但后来他们在1958年1月证明了这个设计
So this spinning is all about making a rocket fly straight.
因此 这种旋转都是为了让火箭直飞
Now getting your rocket engine thrust aligned perfectly with the rest of the spacecraft is never guaranteed
现在 让你的火箭发动机推力与航天器的其他部分完全对齐是永远无法保证的
and if even slightly off-center then the rocket will turn
如果稍微偏离中心 火箭就会转向
so by spinning the rocket stages it helps them fly straight
因此 通过旋转火箭级 可以帮助它们直飞
and it's a combination of the Gyroscopic effect
它是陀螺仪效应的一个组合
and the fact that if there's any off-center thrust it will be averaged out by the rotation.
以及如果有任何偏离中心的推力 它将被旋转平均化的事实
So the Juno I launches of the Explorer satellites are the most obvious example of this
所以朱诺一号发射的探索者卫星是最明显的例子
since you can actually see the spinning upper stage on the pad.
因为你实际上可以看到在发射台上旋转的上面级
Juno I itself was an evolution of the Redstone missile with stretched fuel tanks
朱诺一号本身是红石导弹的进化版 有拉伸的燃料箱
and it used a higher energy fuel known as Hydyne.
而且它使用了一种被称为Hydyne的高能燃料
Although according to some accounts, the inventor of the fuel Mary Sherman Morgan
尽管根据一些说法 这种燃料的发明者玛丽-谢尔曼-摩根
She suggested it should be called bagel because it would be paired with liquid oxygen.
她建议它应该被称为百吉饼 因为它将与液氧搭配
Hydyne was 60% Unsymmetrical dimethylhydrazine, UDMH and 40% Diethylenetriamine, DETA
Hydyne是60%的不对称二甲肼（UDMH）和40%的二乙烯三胺（DETA）
and it delivered about 12% better performance than the standard fuel used in the Redstone.
它的性能比 "红石 "中使用的标准燃料要好12%
The downside of course is that Hydyne was a lot more toxic
当然 缺点是Hydyne的毒性更大
while many people had proven that
而许多人已经证明
the alcohol used to fuel the Redstone was safe enough to drink.
用来为 "红石 "提供燃料的酒精是安全的 可以饮用
the second third and fourth stages of the Juno
朱诺号的第二、第三和第四级
were clusters of off-the-shelf solid rocket motors called baby Sergeants.
是一簇现成的固体火箭发动机 称为 "小警长"
Because they were basically small versions of the larger Sergeant missile the same fuel composition.
因为它们基本上是大型中士导弹的小型版本 燃料成分相同
Each would be about 1.2 meters long 15 centimeters wide
每枚导弹长约1.2米 宽约15厘米
and it generated about 700 kilograms of thrust for six seconds.
并在六秒钟内产生大约700公斤的推力
So the second stage would have 11 of these in a ring.
因此第二级将有11个这样的环形装置
Inside that there would be three more that would be the third stage
在这里面 还有三个是第三级
and then on top of that you would have a final fourth stage with a single rocket motor
然后在这上面你会有一个最后的第四级 有一个单一的火箭发动机
and the Explorer satellite attached on top of that.
和连接在上面的探索者卫星
So the Juno I had these rocket clusters
所以朱诺一号有这些火箭群
and they put them in a structure called the bucket
他们把它们放在一个叫做 "桶 "的结构中
which added some aerodynamic covers so that it wouldn't get damaged
这增加了一些空气动力罩 以便它不会被损坏
and this itself sat on an electrically driven turntable
而这本身就坐在一个电力驱动的转盘上
which at time of launch would be spinning at about 560 rpm.
在发射时 旋转速度约为560rpm
During the flight they would increase the spin rate
在飞行过程中 他们将增加旋转速度
and it would eventually reach about 750 rpm.
并最终达到约750转/分
The reason you changed the spin rate by the way
顺便说一下 你改变旋转速度的原因是什么？
is that it stopped it lingering at any unfortunate frequencies
是为了阻止它在任何不幸的频率上徘徊
which might be in resonance with the rest of the structure
这可能与结构的其他部分发生共振
which could lead to oscillations resonances and damage.
这可能导致振荡共振和损坏
So that spinning bucket is what we are seeing during the takeoff of Juno.
因此 那个旋转的水桶就是我们在朱诺号起飞时看到的东西
So the Juno rocket would fire its engines for 155 seconds
因此 朱诺火箭将点燃它的引擎 持续155秒
and it would accelerate up downrange taking the spacecraft towards space.
它将加速向下 将航天器推向太空
After the engines cut the vehicle would coast upwards
引擎关闭后 飞行器将向上滑行
then the guidance section would separate
然后引导部分将分离
and it would use thrusters to orient the spinning section to point it downrange.
它将使用推进器来确定旋转部分的方向 将其指向下游
And to be clear this isn't as simple as you might think
而且要清楚 这并不像你想象的那么简单
because a lot of it is a spinning mass on the top
因为它的大部分是在顶部旋转的质量
so you have to account for the gyroscopic procession of caused by applying thrust to this.
所以你必须考虑到对其施加推力所引起的陀螺运动
The vehicle would reach apogee at about 360 kilometers six and a half minutes into flight
飞行器将在飞行六分半钟后到达约360公里的远地点
and at that point they would then fire the three stages in sequence
这时 他们将依次发射三级火箭
and each would take like six seconds to fire two seconds to stage
每个阶段需要6秒的时间 2秒的时间来发射
and so about 30 seconds later Explorer 1 would finally get into orbit.
所以大约30秒后 探索者1号终于进入了轨道
And the beauty of this
这其中的妙处
is that the rocket's guidance hardware with the sensors gyroscopes thrusters
火箭的制导硬件与传感器陀螺仪推进器
that didn't need to go all the way into orbit.
并不需要一直进入轨道
They did the job of pointing the final dumb stages in the right direction
它们的工作是将最后的哑巴级指向正确的方向
and then firing them at the right time.
然后在正确的时间发射它们
And that meant that the final three stages could be much lighter much simpler
这意味着最后三级可以更轻更简单
And that really helped them with performance.
而这确实有助于他们的性能
Although I should say that the Explorer 1 satellite
尽管我应该说 探索者1号卫星
was easily the most complex scientific satellite launched at the time.
是当时发射的最复杂的科学卫星
It was packed with more instruments than either Sputnik 1 or Vanguard.
它所装的仪器比斯普特尼克1号和先锋号都多
So yeah spin stabilization it's still a very useful technique and it's still used.
因此 是的 自旋稳定仍然是一个非常有用的技术 而且仍然被使用
Many spacecraft use a solid rocket motor for the final stage
许多航天器在最后一级使用固体火箭发动机
and the most common one in the US are the star series of motors
在美国最常见的是星形系列的发动机
which were developed by Thiokol and I think Northrop Grumman sell them these days.
这是由Thiokol公司开发的 我想Northrop Grumman公司现在也在销售它们
The Star 37 was used as a final boost for Pioneer and Voyager.
星际37被用作先锋号和旅行者号的最后助推器
The Star 48 was used by New Horizons.
新视野号使用的是 "星48"
The number refers to the diameter of the motor casing in inches.
这个数字指的是电机外壳的直径 单位是英寸
So depending upon the mission requirements
因此 根据任务的要求
these motors can be available with steerable thrust vectoring nozzles
这些电机可以提供可转向的推力矢量喷嘴
so they can control and make it fly straight
所以他们可以控制并使其直线飞行
or they can ditch that extra mass and complexity and they can be spin stabilized
或者他们可以抛弃那些额外的质量和复杂性 他们可以进行自旋稳定
and hopefully improving the performance as a result.
并希望因此而提高性能
But that does mean that when they're finished the spacecraft is spinning rapidly
但这确实意味着 当他们完成后 航天器正在快速旋转
and the spacecraft has to handle that spin afterwards
而且航天器必须在事后处理这种旋转
so some spacecraft actually just live with that spin as part of their operation
因此 一些航天器实际上只是生活在这种旋转中 作为其操作的一部分
because it didn't matter what way they're oriented
因为它们的方向并不重要
but others they need to slow down the spin to their operating conditions.
但另一些航天器则需要减缓自旋 使之符合它们的工作条件
Now de-spin can be performed with just regular RCS thrusters
现在 去旋转可以用普通的RCS推进器来执行
but there's actually a really cool trick called yo-yo de-spin
但实际上有一个非常酷的技巧 叫做溜溜球式的去旋转
and what you have here is there's a pair of heavy masses attached to wires
你在这里看到的是有一对连接在电线上的重物
that as the thing is spinning these wires extend out
当这个东西在旋转的时候 这些线就会伸出来
and it slows down the rotation because of the conservation of angular momentum.
由于角动量的守恒 它减缓了旋转速度
The angular momentum of a mass rotating around a central point
一个围绕中心点旋转的质量的角动量
is proportional to the square of the distance to the center.
与到中心的距离的平方成正比
So the cables used in yo-yo de-spin systems are long.
所以溜溜球去旋转系统中使用的电缆是很长的
I know that the Dawn mission it used 12 meter cables with three kilogram masses
我知道 黎明号任务使用了12米长的电缆 质量为3公斤
Also in the case of dawn the dynamics of the unspooling masses were tuned
此外 在黎明号的情况下 解旋质量的动力学被调整了
so that they didn't just slow the rotation of the spacecraft
所以它们不只是减缓航天器的旋转速度
they actually reversed it a little just before release.
它们实际上是在释放前将其逆转了一下
And they actually needed to do this
而且他们实际上需要这样做
because when the satellite is spinning
因为当卫星在旋转的时候
the fuel tanks inside it the liquid is spinning inside that
它里面的燃料罐 液体在里面旋转
and when they stopped it spinning the fuel continues to spin
而当他们停止旋转时 燃料继续旋转
so by having it giving a little backwards spin as the fuel slows down and equalizes
所以通过让它在燃料减慢和平衡的时候给予一点反向的旋转
it all ends up cancelling out and the entire satellite stops spinning neatly
所有这些最终都被抵消了 整个卫星整齐地停止了旋转
and then it can go about and do its mission.
然后它就可以去做它的任务了
So yo-yo de-spin is generally not used for spacecraft that are intended to stay in earth orbit
所以溜溜球式的去旋转一般不用于打算留在地球轨道上的航天器
because it creates extra space debris.
因为它会产生额外的空间碎片
It's used for sub-orbital sounding rockets because they are falling back to earth
它被用于亚轨道探空火箭 因为它们正在落回地球
and that there actually is a very fast way of de-spinning the rocket.
而且实际上有一种非常快速的方法来使火箭脱旋
And also it's used for missions to deep space.
此外 它还被用于深空任务
There is at least one case I know where a mass that was used for a de-spin system
我知道至少有一个案例 一个用于去旋转系统的质量
was a collision hazard for the international space station.
是国际空间站的一个碰撞危险
But also it's kind of cool to think there's a pair of these like dumb masses
但是 想到有一对这样的哑巴质量 也是一种很酷的事情
headed out of the solar system at escape velocity
以逃逸的速度离开太阳系
and because they were used in the New Horizons spacecraft
因为它们被用在新视野号飞船上
and if you think about it
如果你想一想
these discarded masses they're effectively lost in space.
这些被丢弃的质量 它们实际上已经在太空中消失了
In fact these ones New Horizons are probably the most lost in space object created by humans
事实上 这些新视野号可能是人类创造的最迷失在太空的物体
because they're so small
因为它们是如此之小
we could never see them and we don't know their original orbit
我们永远无法看到它们 我们也不知道它们的原始轨道
so they're total mysteries out there.
所以它们在那里完全是个谜
But finally I want to come back to Explorer 1
但最后我想回到探索者1号上
because the spin actually led to an unexpected scientific observation
因为旋转实际上导致了一个意外的科学观察
so the satellite was originally rotating around its longitudinal axis around its long axis like a bullet
所以这颗卫星最初是围绕其纵轴旋转的 就像一颗子弹一样
but over time it transitioned to a slower rotation mode when an end over ends tumbling motion
但随着时间的推移 它过渡到一个较慢的旋转模式 即端部翻滚运动
and this actually confused the engineers
而这实际上使工程师们感到困惑
because conservation of energy and angular momentum should have kept it stable.
因为能量和角动量的守恒应该使它保持稳定
It's objects spinning in a vacuum what's going to change things.
在真空中旋转的物体才会改变事情
Generally objects will spin around preferred axis
一般来说 物体会围绕首选轴旋转
if you try to spin it around another axis which is not stable
如果你试图让它围绕另一个不稳定的轴旋转
it will flip orientation and there's this great video on the space station of this.
它就会翻转方向 在空间站上有这样一个很好的视频
T-shaped handle flipping between two rotational orientations
T型手柄在两个旋转方向之间的翻转
because that's not one of his preferred orientations.
因为这不是他喜欢的方向之一
So Explorer 1 should have been stable around its original rotational axis
所以探索者1号应该是围绕其原始的旋转轴稳定的
because a change to any other rotational axis
因为如果改变任何其他的旋转轴
would require it to change its rotational kinetic energy
就需要改变它的旋转动能
and that in a vacuum is hard right where's it getting rid of it
而这在真空中是很难做到的 它在哪里能摆脱它呢？
but it turns out that after it was released it deployed flexible antenna
但事实证明 在它被释放后 它部署了灵活的天线
and as these were perturbed they would flex
当这些天线受到扰动时 它们会弯曲
and the flexing would actually convert a small amount of the kinetic energy into heat
弯曲实际上会把少量的动能转换成热能
and as it did this it meant that the thing had to rotate more slowly
当它这样做的时候 意味着这个东西必须更慢地旋转
and to rotate more slowly it had to change its rotational axis
为了旋转得更慢 它必须改变它的旋转轴线
so over time these flexible antennas drove the rotation into the slower end over end state.
因此 随着时间的推移 这些灵活的天线促使旋转进入较慢的端对端状态
And that's actually important for modern satellite design
而这实际上对现代卫星设计很重要
because you want to make sure that if your satellite is going to be rotating
因为你要确保 如果你的卫星要旋转的话
that it's not going to flip into another rotational state because it dissipates energy.
它不会因为耗散能量而翻转到另一个旋转状态
And yeah this is a cool thing because Explorer 1 would never have observed this
是的 这是一个很酷的事情 因为如果不是因为设计 探索者1号永远不会观察到这个
if it wasn't for the design of the spacecraft being optimized around this spin stabilized hack
如果不是因为航天器的设计是围绕这个自旋稳定的黑客进行优化的
trying to put things into orbit as quickly as possible.
试图尽快把东西送入轨道
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是斯科特-曼利 飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]